Inventory of the John Franklin Carter papers, 1902-1979
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
John Franklin Carter papers
1902-1979
Carter, John Franklin, 1897-1967
01670
10.30 cubic ft. (23 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Contains materials relating to Carter's work as a journalist and author of fiction.
Biography of John Franklin Carter
John Franklin Carter was a New Deal columnist syndicated under the pen name of Jay Franklin. He was the author of more than 30 books of fiction and nonfiction. Carter attended Yale where he formed a network of important contacts. After a brief career in government service, he became the Rome correspondent for the London Daily Chronicle in 1922. A year later he moved to the New York Times. In 1928 he became an economic specialist for the Division of Western Europe for the U.S. State Department. He was Washington correspondent for Liberty magazine, but returned to government service from 1934 to 1936 as Under Secretary for Agriculture. Carter was best known for his syndicated column "We the People," which ran 1936-1948.
Carter supported Franklin Roosevelt’s New Deal policies and acted as an advisor on “political intelligence” to the president during World War II. He was also a radio commentator for NBC from 1938 to 1939. Carter later worked for Harry Truman as a speechwriter but resigned from the White House staff shortly after Truman's election. He joined the Republican Party and became an active supporter of President Richard Nixon. Carter became an economic research consultant for the New York State Department of Commerce. In 1950, he was appointed director of public relations for the New York State Publicity Department. He died in 1967.
Scope and Content
The John Franklin Carter papers include correspondence, numerous manuscripts, books, some photographs and other biographical material. Most of this material relates to American political and diplomatic events from World War I through World War II. The correspondence and manuscript portions of this collection are extensive and they express Carter's expert opinions of his time.
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
An oral history interview with John Franklin Carter can be found at the Truman Library, along with correspondence and other related materials throughout the Library's collections.
This material was received from Sheila Carter, Sonia Carter Greenbaum, and Kenneth DeKay between 1965 and 1974. Additional material was received in 2020.
Access Terms
Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; London Daily Chronicle.; New York Times Company.; Political campaigns -- United States.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Diplomacy.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Intelligence service.; Journalists -- 20th century; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972; Franklin, Jay, 1897-1967
Politics, Government, and Law; Journalism; Publishers and Publishing; Military; Politics and Politicians
Container List
- Series I. Biographical
  Contains personal and family memorabilia with some life histories. Arranged alphabetically by type.
  - Biographical information, 1919-1950 (Box 1)
  - Carter, John F., obituaries, list of publications, Who’s Who, draft status cards,Yale clippings, passports, 1918-1967 (Box 1)
  - Carter, Sheila Sutherland, correspondence, baptismal records, marriage certificate, 1927-1973 (Box 1)
  - Clippings – advertisements for The Messiah, The New Dealers, etc., 1934-1935 (Box 1)
  - Clippings – articles, reviews, 1924-1936 (Box 1)
  - Clippings – Madam President (5 part serial in Colliers), 1948 (Box 1)
  - Clippings – Man Is War reviews, 1926-1927 (Box 1)
  - Family, correspondence, certificates, obituary, 1929-1969 (Box 1)
  - Financial, will, estate contracts, etc., 1933-1961 (Box 1)
  - Invitations, programs, press passes, cards, certificates, C.E.A.S.E. newsletter, 1932-1950 (Box 1)
  - Legal documents: Warshawsky vs. Carter, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Oral history of Truman Campaign, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Portrait sketch, undated (Box 1)
  - Schoolwork, daily essays, class notes, 1917-1918 (Box 1)
  - W.H.S. (Yale - Fraternal Organization?), 1921-1959 (Box 1)
- Series II. Correspondence
  Contains family letters and professional communications. Arranged chronologically.
  - Italy, 1907-1918 (Box 2)
  - Italy, Constantinople, 1919 (Box 2)
  - Europe, U.S., Diplomatic Service, 1920-1929 (Box 2)
  - Europe, U.S., newspaper correspondent, 1930-1939 (Box 2)
  - World War II, White House Intelligence, 1940-1945 (Box 2)
  - Post-war author, political aide, 1946-1947 (Box 2)
  - Post Truman election, 1948 (Box 2)
  - Various, Truman political, 1949-1950 (Box 2)
  - Author, writer, 1951-1955 (Box 2)
  - Author, deaths, legal, 1956-1960 (Box 2)
  - Honors, Republican politics, 1961-1965 (Box 3)
  - War reminiscences, politics, 1966-1967, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Varied, personal, undated (Box 3)
- Series III. Diaries
  Entries include weather, appointments, and some observations. Arranged chronologically.
  - W. Straker Diary for 1914 (Box 3)
  - John F. Carter, Jr., A Journal (manuscript and original journal), 1918 (Box 3)
  - “For Sheila...,”, 1932 (Box 3)
  - The Year 1948 (Box 3)
  - Date Book, 1949 (Box 3)
  - Diary for Any Year, 1949 (Box 4)
  - 1950 Daily Desk Diary, Appointments, Memoranda, Reminders (Box 4)
  - National Diary 1952 (Box 4)
  - Date Book, 1953 (Box 4)
  - Date Book 1954 (Box 4)
  - Date Book 1955 (Box 5)
  - Date Book 1956 (Box 5)
  - Date Book 1957 (Box 5)
  - Five Year Diary, 1958 (Box 5)
  - National Diary for 1960 (Box 6)
  - One Year Diary, 1962 (Box 6)
  - National Diary for 1964 (Box 6)
  - National Diary for 1965 (Box 6)
  - National Diary for 1967 (Box 6)
- Series IV. Manuscripts
  Most items address politics and foreign policy. Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Sub-series 1: Books, Articles, 1913-1965
    - Partial – Chapter One, undated (Box 7)
    - The Abandoned, undated (Box 7)
    - The A. G. Assignment, undated (Box 7)
    - The A. G. Caper, undated (Box 7)
    - The Academic Accident at Center, undated (Box 7)
    - The Incident at Center, undated (Box 7)
    - Adolf Hitler – Manuscript by Putz Hautptaenzi, 1942 (Box 7)
    - The American Mandate, 1948 (Box 7)
    - Bombs Bursting in Air, undated (Box 7)
    - “City of Destruction” chapter, title unknown, undated (Box 7)
    - “The Creation of Annie Girdler,” Kearney’s Captive, Part II, undated (Box 7)
    - Creative Conservatism, undated (Box 7)
    - The Curses of the Mattanuxent, undated (Box 7)
    - The Drew Pearson Story (Part 1) by Frank L. Kluckhohn, undated (Box 7)
    - The Drew Pearson Story (Part II) by Frank L. Kluckhohn, undated (Box 8)
    - The End of the New Deal, undated (Box 8)
    - Excavations of Glastonbury and Predictions of Things to Come Through the Script Writings of John Alleyne, undated (Box 8)
    - Handbook for Republicans, undated (Box 8)
    - Hangover Hall, 1947 (Box 8)
    - Hell’s Bells, undated (Box 8)
    - Here’s Where I Come In, undated (Box 8)
    - His Name Was Susan (an outline treatment), undated (Box 8)
    - How We Drafted Roosevelt, undated (Box 8)
    - The Language of Love, undated (Box 8)
    - The Longest Way Around, Part I, 1918-1928 (Autobiographical), undated (Box 9)
    - Man Is War, undated (Box 9)
    - The Mice, undated (Box 9)
    - Navarino, undated (Box 9)
    - A Needed Reform, 1913 (Box 9)
    - 1940 and After, undated (Box 10)
    - N.P.C. – 1997 A.D., undated (Box 10)
    - One Man in His Time – Part II, The Age of Consent, undated (Box 10)
    - The Past Has Power, undated (Box 10)
    - The Plow that Broke the Plains (U.S. Resettlement Administration), undated (Box 10)
    - President Truman and the Negroes, 1949 (Box 10)
    - Princess Royal, undated (Box 10)
    - The Prize for Panic, undated (Box 10)
    - The R. E. Runaround, undated (Box 10)
    - The R. E. Runaround, undated (Box 11)
    - Remember Me, undated (Box 11)
    - The Seventh American Revolution, circa 1963-1964 (Box 11)
    - The Seventh American Revolution, circa 1963-1964 (Box 12)
    - The Seventh American Revolution (for posthumous publication), circa 1963-1964 (Box 12)
    - The Seventh American Revolution, Part II (for posthumous publication), circa 1963-1964 (Box 13)
    - The Seventh American Revolution, Part III (for posthumous publication), circa 1963-1964 (Box 13)
    - The Seventh American Revolution (for posthumous publication), circa 1963-1964 (Box 13)
    - The Seventh American Revolution, Part I (for posthumous publication), circa 1963-1964 (Box 13)
    - The Seventh American Revolution, Part II (for posthumous publication), circa 1963-1964 (Box 13)
    - The Seventh American Revolution, Part III (for posthumous publication), circa 1963-1964 (Box 13)
    - The Shortest Night of the Year, undated (Box 13)
    - The Sin of the Littlest Angel, undated (Box 13)
    - A Slight Delay in Service, 1965 (Box 13)
    - Something Lost Beyond the Mountains, (Part I), undated (Box 14)
    - Something Lost Beyond the Mountains, (Part II), undated (Box 14)
    - Star in the West: The Way Out of the Twentieth Century, (Part I), undated (Box 14)
    - Star in the West: The Way Out of the Twentieth Century, (Part II), undated (Box 14)
    - The System and the Game by Pen Name, undated (Box 14)
    - Ten Thousand Piccolos (1 of 2), undated (Box 15)
    - Ten Thousand Piccolos, by “Diplomat” (2 of 2), undated (Box 15)
    - The Terra Cotta Parachute, undated (Box 15)
    - This Day and Age (2), undated (Box 15)
    - Unarmed for Armageddon (for posthumous publication), undated (Box 16)
    - Wally’s Sixth Wife, undated (Box 16)
    - We the People, “A Good Job Well Done,”, 1948 (Box 16)
    - We the People, “The Yanks Cross the Rhine,”, 1945 (Box 16)
    - The Year of Crisis – 1943 (Autobiographical), undated (Box 17)
    - “West Virginia Manhunt” (partial, 2 copies), undated (Box 17)
    - Wild Geese that Stormed the Gale, undated (Box 17)
    - The Wings of an Angel, undated (Box 17)
    - The Year of the Elections, 1932 (Box 17)
    - A Year on Olympus (autobiographical), undated (Box 17)
    - You Sons, books 1-2, undated (Box 17)
    - You Sons, books 3-4, undated (Box 17)
  - Sub-series 2: Plays, undated
    - As You Were, undated (Box 18)
    - Henry and the Grim Reaper, undated (Box 18)
    - The Mice, undated (Box 18)
    - The Mutiny, undated (Box 18)
    - Nobody’s Business, undated (Box 18)
    - The Open Sluice, undated (Box 18)
    - Tancred, undated (Box 18)
    - Uncle’s Conversion, undated (Box 18)
  - Sub-series 3: Other manuscripts, 1900-1940
    - Poetry, circa 1910-1940 (Box 18)
    - Short stories, essays, and reports including We the People, circa 1910-1940 (Box 19)
    - Speeches, circa 1910-1940 (Box 19)
- Series V. Photographs
  Contains personal, family, and professional portraits.
  - Photographs, 1902 - circa 1940 (Box 19)
- Series VI. Radio Broadcasts
  Contains Carter’s NBC Radio political commentaries. Arranged chronologically.
  - Jay Franklin, 1938 June - September (Box 20)
  - Jay Franklin, 1938 September - 1939 March (Box 20)
  - News Releases, 1938-1939 (Box 20)
- Series VII. Subject Files
  Includes a variety of headings such as autographs, politics, New York politics, Canada, and conservation. Arranged alphabetically by subject heading.
  - Autographs (originals in safe), circa 1940s (Box 20)
  - Bender, George, circa 1940s (Box 20)
  - Canada, Winnipeg, etc., circa 1937 (Box 20)
  - Clippings and pamphlets, circa 1950s (Box 20)
  - Nagle résumé, notes, lists, 1926 - circa 1940 (Box 20)
  - New National Party, “New Party,”, undated (Box 20)
  - New York State Legislature – agenda, minutes, 1957 (Box 20)
  - New York State Legislature – reports, 1956-1957 (Box 20)
  - New York State Legislature – reports, 1938-circa 1957 (Box 21)
  - Notes: Germany and the Nazi Party, Hitler, Geering, undated (Box 21)
  - Politics, circa 1950s (Box 21)
  - Politics, 1939-1941 (Box 21)
  - Publicity, 1939-1948 (Box 21)
  - Published Articles, Harper’s Book Review, Cimarron Review, 1957-1979 (Box 21)
  - Range Conservation, 1947 (Box 21)
  - Speeches, “Speech of the Week,”, circa 1960s (Box 21)
  - Stationery – Adolph Hitler, 1945 (Box 21)
- Series VIII. Research Cards
  Contains subject and bibliographical cards for three political/historical books. Arranged alphabetically.
  - The American Conquest, undated (Box 22)
  - Man Is War, undated (Box 22)
  - Near Eastern Question, undated (Box 22)
- Series IX. Published Books and Photocopied Material
  Contains political books by Carter and copies of Yale College songs.
  - Photocopied Biographical Material from Yale Archives, undated (Box 23)
  - Book - The Catoctin Conversation, by Jay Franklin (Carter), 1947 (Box 23)
  - Journal - The Cimarron Review, “As I Saw Them: FDR, HST, DDE, JFK, LBJ” by John Franklin Carter, 1979 (Box 23)
  - Book - The Drew Pearson Story by Jay Franklin (Carter) and Frank Kluckhohn (annotated to Gene Gressley from Sheila Carter), 1967 (Box 23)
  - Book - 1940 by Jay Franklin (Carter) and comments by Sir Willmott Lewis of the London Times (Box 23)
  - Book - Remaking America by Jay Franklin (Carter), 1942 (Box 23)